<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  xlxs4  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://xlxs4.github.io </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  The Lorekeeper archives.  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://xlxs4.github.io/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  ESA Design Booster  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://xlxs4.github.io/notes/esa-design-booster/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://xlxs4.github.io/notes/esa-design-booster/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A visit in ESA &#40;Netherlands&#41; for the design booster week  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<div class="page-tag"><i class="fa fa-tag"></i><a href="https://xlxs4.github.io/tag/esa/">esa</a>, <a href="https://xlxs4.github.io/tag/space/">space</a></div><div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>ESA Design Booster<ol><li>Getting There</li></ol></li></ol></div>
<h2 id="esa_design_booster">ESA Design Booster</h2>
<p>The <a href="https://www.esa.int/Education/CubeSats_-_Fly_Your_Satellite/Fly_Your_Satellite&#33;_Design_Booster_pilot?fbclid&#61;IwAR3hcjAva089hKRr8a74cB60zLhuBLy3mbpIcjtmc6AKB5Er1PXpcs9zvpw">Fly Your Satellite&#33; Design Booster</a> is a pilot program of the <a href="https://www.esa.int/">European Space Agency &#40;ESA&#41;</a>. It&#39;s aimed at students working in the design of a CubeSat mission. <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/CubeSat">CubeSat</a>s are miniaturized satellites that have standardized form — in LEGO brick fashion, they&#39;re shaped as \(n \ge 1\) 10cm cubes, stacked vertically. It&#39;s an idea to accelerate and democratize space missions<sup id="fnref:1">[1]</sup>, cutting down on the cost<sup id="fnref:2">[2]</sup> and effort required to get the spacecraft in-orbit.</p>
<p>Design Booster aims to assist the teams by providing further training during the full project lifecycle and across a wide spectrum of areas from aerospace engineering to project management or even operating the CubeSat while it&#39;s in-orbit. The program is split in distinct phases that are adapted from the typical development cycle of space missions and it follows a fixed scheduled spanning 1.5 years. In brief, the teams first have to apply to the program. Then, the shortlisted teams undergo the &quot;Training and Selection&quot; phase where they receive training from ESA experts and in about a month after they have to defend their proposed design in front of a panel of ESA experts. The selected teams continue on to the next phase, &quot;Baseline Design Review&quot; where they have to baseline their design which is then assessed by the experts. After this two-month phase is concluded, the teams have about a year to finalize their design. The program ends with the so-called &quot;Final Design Review&quot;, where the design undergoes through examination to check whether the design has been successfully consolidated.</p>
<h3 id="getting_there">Getting There</h3>
<p>The &quot;Training and Selection&quot; phase kicked off with presentations from ESA experts in Nov. 7. I was invited to give a talk to share some insight on how working at a long-term space mission project can be, with an addendum on the challenges behind trying to run Space Biology experiments inside a CubeSat. I flew from Greece to Munich, Munich to Amsterdam, took the train to Leiden and there I was on a rainy day&#33;</p>
<figure class="figure">
  <img src="./assets/leiden-centraal.jpg" alt="The Leiden Centraal train station." class="figure-img img-fluid " width="" >
  <figcaption class="figure-caption ">
The Leiden Centraal train station.
</figcaption></figure><p>The training workshop was hosted in the <a href="https://www.esa.int/About_Us/ESTEC/European_Space_Research_and_Technology_Centre_ESTEC2">ESA ESTEC</a> facilities. ESTEC is in Noordwijk, a small town by the sea somewhere in the Netherlands. It&#39;s the larger site and the technical heart of ESA. I got to navigate through the facilities inside an autonomous shuttle bus you could drive with a joystick and a touchscreen&#33;</p>
<figure class="figure">
  <img src="./assets/exomars.jpg" alt="<a href='https://www.esa.int/Science_Exploration/Human_and_Robotic_Exploration/Exploration/ExoMars'>Exomars</a> — has life ever existed on Mars?" class="figure-img img-fluid " width="" >
  <figcaption class="figure-caption ">
<a href='https://www.esa.int/Science_Exploration/Human_and_Robotic_Exploration/Exploration/ExoMars'>Exomars</a> — has life ever existed on Mars?
</figcaption></figure><p><table class="fndef" id="fndef:1">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[1]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">Poghosyan, A., &amp; Golkar, A. &#40;2017&#41;. CubeSat evolution: Analyzing CubeSat capabilities for conducting science missions. <em>Progress in Aerospace Sciences, 88</em>, 59-83.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:2">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[2]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">Sweeting, M. &#40;2018&#41;. Modern small satellites-changing the economics of space. <em>Proceedings of the IEEE, 106&#40;3&#41;</em>, 343-361.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
</p>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Orestis Ousoultzoglou</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>